Baltimore, MD

410.980.9672 (cell) bheussler@gmail.com

Summary

I am a software developer whose skills and interests lie at the intersection between Semantic Web and Big Data. For over a year I have worked for iNovex Information Systems on the Independent Research and Development program. On occasion, I will provide consulting services to our partner Cambridge Semantics, who provide enterprise level Semantic Web products to commercial customers.

Experience

Accumulo Data Integration Prototype

iNovex Information Systems August 2013 - October 2013

Software Developer

- Handled a variety of data in large volumes by integrating data before it was written to Accumulo, which improved data retrieval at the application layer
- Dynamically applied provenance information based on the PROV-O provenance ontology to all data headed for Accumulo, which provided lineage to all data read from Accumulo
- Integrated structured, semi-structured, and unstructured data using W3C Semantic Web standards, which yielded inherent data layer linkages between like or similar entities from disparate data sets

Hive Metadata Extractor

Cambridge Semantics

Big Data Consultant

June 2013 - July 2013

- Provided metadata to existing query completion and database schema facilities by extracting metadata from Hive using Java and JDBC
- Improved customer's existing product by adding a feature to allow ingestion of data from Hive data warehouse

Economic Volatility Genetic Algorithm

Connecticut College

Studen

January 2012 - May 2012

- Forecasted economic volatility using a genetic algorithm, which improved on the traditional technique of regression analysis
- Performed interdisciplinary research under professors Gary Parker (Computer Science) and Purba Mukerji (Economics)

Education

Connecticut College

New London, CT

B.A. Major Computer Science, Minor Economics (GPA 3.28)

Aug. 2008 - May. 2012

 Relevant Courses: Computational Intelligence, Artificial Intelligence, Networks, Algorithms, Data Structures, Computer Organization, Topics in Software Development

University of Nottingham

Nottingham, UK

Study Abroad

Sept. 2010 - Jan. 2011

Relevant Courses: Operations Research and Optimization, Knowledge Representation and Reasoning,
Graphical User Interfaces, Software Engineering Methodologies, Introduction to Formal Reasoning

Skills

Languages: Experience with Java (Proficient), Bash (Competent), SPARQL (Competent), SQL (Competent), Python (Prior Experience), Javascript (Prior Experience) and Scheme (Prior Experience)

Certifications: Oracle Certified Associate, Java SE 7 Programmer

Misc: Experience with Git, Subversion, Maven, Ant, OSGI, Eclipse, Linux, and Windows